<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-GB"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-GB" /><updated>2025-11-19T20:47:39+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Steven R. Schofield Research Group</title><subtitle>The Schofield Group at UCL, led by Professor Steven R. Schofield, studies quantum nanoscience using scanning tunnelling microscopy and related techniques.</subtitle><author><name>Steven R. Schofield</name></author><entry><title type="html">Visiting Researcher Dr Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda (ICMCB Bordeaux) Introduces the Lab to Spin-Crossover Self-Assembled Monolayers (SCO-SAMs)</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/14/Rebecca-Bordeaux-Visit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting Researcher Dr Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda (ICMCB Bordeaux) Introduces the Lab to Spin-Crossover Self-Assembled Monolayers (SCO-SAMs)" /><published>2025-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/14/Rebecca-Bordeaux-Visit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/14/Rebecca-Bordeaux-Visit/"><![CDATA[<p>This week marks the end of a successful visit to our group by <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/rrodriguesdem">Dr Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda</a> from the <a href="https://www.icmcb-bordeaux.cnrs.fr/en/">Institute of Condensed Matter Chemistry of Bordeaux (ICMCB)</a>.</p>

<p>Rebecca’s research focuses on <em>spin-crossover (SCO) compounds</em>—a fascinating class of molecular materials that can reversibly switch between low-spin and high-spin states in response to external stimuli such as temperature, pressure, or light. This switching is often accompanied by large changes in magnetic, optical, and electronic properties, making SCO molecules strong candidates for future molecular-scale sensors, memories, and logic devices.</p>

<p>Rebecca, a postdoctoral researcher working with <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/mathieu-gonidec-a270632b">Dr Mathieu Gonidec</a> at ICMCB–CNRS,  became interested in SCOs during her PhD under the supervision of <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/patrick-rosa-b664141b">Dr Patrick Rosa</a>. Together with their team, they demonstrated that an iron(II) SCO compound functionalised with a long alkyl chain exhibits <em>reversibly switchable</em> behaviour when formed into a self-assembled monolayer (SAM) on gold substrates (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsnano.5c11659">ACS Nano 19, 36566–36577 (2025)</a>). This result is particularly noteworthy because direct contact between SCO molecules and a metallic substrate often suppresses or “pins” their switchable behaviour, undermining their potential for device applications.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-11-14_Rebecca_ICMBC.jpg" alt="Dr. Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda visiting the LCN at UCL" />
  <figcaption>Dr Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda transferring liquid nitrogen to the low-temperature scanning tunnelling microscope (LT-STM) during her visit to the London Centre for Nanotechnology, UCL (Nov 2025).</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The goal of Rebecca’s visit to UCL was to use our ultrahigh-vacuum low-temperature scanning tunnelling microscope (UHV LT-STM) to image these SAMs with atomic resolution. Despite previously  employing a range of analytical techniques to probe the structural, electronic, and magnetic properties of these layers, open questions remain regarding their atomic-scale structure. One key question concerns the adsorption geometry of the SCO molecules: whether the intended thiol headgroup always binds directly to the gold surface, or whether the molecule sometimes folds so that the SCO “head” group also interacts with the substrate. High-resolution STM imaging, complemented by tunnelling spectroscopy and comparison with density-functional-theory calculations, will help answer this question and shed light on the conformation of the adsorbates and how substrate interactions affect spin switching at the single-molecule level.</p>

<p>The first step in preparing the SAMs is to produce what are known as template-stripped gold substrates. This is done by evaporating a 200-nm layer of gold onto a silicon wafer and then attaching a small glass substrate to the gold film. The samples were brought from France in this form. Once at UCL, the gold surface was exposed by removing the silicon wafer to reveal an atomically flat, pristine gold surface. The samples were then mounted onto an STM sample plate using a UHV-compatible conductive epoxy, which was cured by annealing below 375 K before being transferred to the STM for imaging.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-11-14_Rebecca_TSAu.jpg" alt="STM image of template stripped gold" />
  <figcaption>Preparing and imaging a template-stripped gold substrate prior to forming the self-assembled monolayer.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The next stage was to prepare the SAMs. Freshly exposed gold substrates were immersed in a solution of the SCO compound in methanol, with a small amount of triethylamine to activate the molecules for binding to the gold surface. The vials were purged with nitrogen and left sealed for 24 hours to allow the SAMs to form. After incubation, the substrates were rinsed with methanol, dried under nitrogen, and, after being mounted on STM sample plates, transferred into UHV where they were degassed overnight.</p>

<p>The STM data we obtained during this short visit were promising. We imaged extended atomically flat regions of clean gold on the pristine template-stripped samples and resolved the surface structure of the SAMs prepared under several different conditions. Imaging and tunnelling spectroscopy were performed both at room temperature and at 77 K.</p>

<p>The collaboration proved mutually beneficial, and we learned a great deal from Rebecca, even achieving several firsts for our laboratory during her visit. The template-stripped gold preparation method is something we have been aiming to establish in our lab to produce atomically flat gold surfaces suitable for transferring monolayer and few-layer flakes of two-dimensional materials. From Rebecca we learned several important details about the preparation of these samples, which will be carried forward into future experiments on exfoliated two-dimensional materials planned for 2026.</p>

<p>Moreover, Rebecca’s visit marks the first time that <em>ex-situ</em> fabricated SAMs—or <em>ex-situ</em> chemically prepared samples of any kind—have been successfully imaged in our laboratory. This represents an important step for us toward combining wet-chemical sample preparation with atomic-scale UHV characterisation.</p>

<p>Rebecca’s visit has opened up the potential for future collaborations between our group and researchers in Bordeaux, or with other groups working in related areas, combining expertise in molecular synthesis, thin-film preparation, and atomic-scale characterisation.</p>

<p><em>Rebecca gratefully acknowledges the support of <a href="https://quantum-matter-bordeaux.cnrs.fr">Quantum Matter Bordeaux (QMBx)</a> for funding her visit.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="visitors" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="molecular-electronics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rebecca Rodrigues de Miranda’s two-week visit explores spin-crossover compounds on gold surfaces using STM.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-11-14_Rebecca_ICMBC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-11-14_Rebecca_ICMBC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CMMP Seminar by Prof. Michael Flatté (U. Iowa / TU Eindhoven)</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/07/Michael-Flatte-CMMP-Seminar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CMMP Seminar by Prof. Michael Flatté (U. Iowa / TU Eindhoven)" /><published>2025-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/07/Michael-Flatte-CMMP-Seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/11/07/Michael-Flatte-CMMP-Seminar/"><![CDATA[<p>We were delighted to host <a href="https://physics.uiowa.edu/people/michael-flatte">Prof. Michael E. Flatté</a> from the University of Iowa for his recent visit to UCL.</p>

<p>Michael is a long-standing collaborator and regular visitor to our group. This visit combined two highlights: continuing our collaborative work with his PhD student, Niels van Venrooij, and delivering an invited seminar to the Condensed Matter and Materials Physics (CMMP) group.</p>

<p>Niels is undertaking a research visit with us, working on projects that bridge experiment and theory. One of these, now nearing completion, examines interference effects in photoemission from silicon nanostructures. He is also developing new models to describe correlations in dilute dopant networks—an important step toward understanding the collective behaviour of dopants in semiconductors.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-11-07_Flatte-Niels.jpeg" alt="Prof. Michael E. Flatté with Niels van Venrooij and Steven Schofield at UCL" />
  <figcaption>PhD student Niels van Venrooij, Prof. Steven Schofield, and Prof. Michael E. Flatté in the Academic Staff Common Room, UCL (29 Oct 2025).</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>During his visit, Michael also delivered a thought-provoking seminar to the CMMP group of the Department of Physics and Astronomy entitled <em>“Dopants in Semiconductors – ‘Artificial Atoms’ for Quantum Technologies?”</em></p>

<p>In his talk, he explored why semiconductor-based quantum computers have yet to achieve the scalability originally envisioned. While dopants in semiconductors were once seen as ideal building blocks for quantum technologies, offering discrete energy states and the promise of scalability, progress has been slower than anticipated.</p>

<p>He explained that the number of qubits achieved in semiconductor systems remains an order of magnitude or more below that realised in superconducting or trapped-ion platforms. A major challenge, he noted, lies in noise introduced by control gates and electrodes, which can be a severe impediment to qubit coherence times. Moreover, whereas classical CMOS technology is inherently digital, quantum systems are not, and this mismatch poses difficulties: each qubit often requires individual tuning to achieve uniform performance. Even dopant-based qubits, often described as “identical,” can vary due to differences in their local crystal environment.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-11-07_Flatte-CMMP.jpg" alt="Seminar slide for Michael Flatté’s talk at UCL" />
  <figcaption>Prof. Michael E. Flatté’s CMMP seminar at UCL: <em>“Dopants in Semiconductors – ‘Artificial Atoms’ for Quantum Technologies?”</em></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Throughout the seminar, Michael illustrated these ideas with striking examples that combined experiment and theory. His talk ranged from nitrogen-vacancy centres in diamond and silicon carbide to dopants in III–V and group-IV semiconductors, including recent collaborative work with our group on <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c02675">acceptor states in silicon</a>. He also suggested that using superconducting gates in semiconductor architectures could offer a path to mitigating electrical noise in future quantum circuits.</p>

<p>As always, Michael’s visit was intellectually stimulating and strengthened our ongoing collaborations in semiconductor quantum devices and spin-based quantum technologies. We eagerly look forward to his next visit.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="visitors" /><category term="seminars" /><category term="collaboration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Michael Flatté’s visit to UCL sparks fresh discussion on the challenges facing semiconductor-based quantum computing.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-11-07_Flatte-Niels.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-11-07_Flatte-Niels.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Successful Research Visit from IISc Bangalore</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/31/Hardeep-Visit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Successful Research Visit from IISc Bangalore" /><published>2025-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/31/Hardeep-Visit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/31/Hardeep-Visit/"><![CDATA[<p>This week marks the end of a six-week visit by Hardeep, a PhD student from Akshay Singh’s group at the Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore. His visit was supported by a <a href="https://royalsociety.org/grants/international-exchanges/">Royal Society International Exchanges</a> grant, with the initial contact made possible through the <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/global/ucl-global-engagement">UCL Global Engagement scheme</a>.</p>

<p>It has been a pleasure hosting Hardeep in our lab. During his visit, he learned to operate most aspects of our ultrahigh-vacuum scanning tunnelling microscope (UHV-STM) and the associated equipment. Despite being new to these techniques, his enthusiasm and experience as a third-year PhD student at IISc soon made him a positive role model for our two new students. Over the course of his visit, he mastered the operation of the UHV-STM and even helped troubleshoot the system when the occasion arose.</p>

<p>Hardeep brought to our lab valuable knowledge and skills related to the preparation of 2D materials for optical measurements, and he will leave with an entirely new skill set in preparing samples for ultrahigh-vacuum conditions and performing atomic-scale measurements with STM. The knowledge exchange facilitated by his visit extends beyond sample preparation—the initial stages of analysing the data he obtained have already introduced him to new concepts in condensed matter physics, and it will be exciting to see how this develops as the work of processing, analysing, and interpreting the data continues. Hardeep also participated actively in our weekly group meetings, giving a talk on his previous research and contributing thoughtfully to discussions on the work of other group members.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-10-31_hardeep.jpg" alt="Hardeep Singh in the STM lab" />
  <figcaption>Hardeep in the STM lab during his six-week visit to UCL.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The goals of his visit were to investigate defects in molybdenum disulfide (MoS<sub>2</sub>) and to develop methods for contacting and imaging monolayer flakes of exfoliated two-dimensional materials. We made excellent progress on both fronts, which places Hardeep in a strong position for his return visit to UCL, planned for 2026. During his stay, we successfully imaged bulk MoS<sub>2</sub> samples with atomic resolution and investigated defect structures. The resulting data are promising, and the analysis and interpretation will continue collaboratively after Hardeep’s return to Bangalore.</p>

<p>In addition to the STM work, Hardeep received training to access several of our other laboratories, including facilities for optical microscopy—equipment similar to what he regularly uses at IISc. These complementary techniques allow us to study our samples across vastly different length scales, from optical to atomic resolution. Through this combined work, we are developing the capability to investigate monolayer 2D samples alongside bulk materials, broadening the scope of our joint research. It will be exciting to see how the analysis of our data proceeds over the coming months as we simultaneously develop plans for the measurements we will make during Hardeep’s return visit in 2026.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-10-31_hardeep_mos2.jpg" alt="STM image of MoS2 obtained during Hardeep's visit" />
  <figcaption>Atomic-resolution STM image of molybdenum disulfide (MoS<sub>2</sub>) obtained during Hardeep’s visit.</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="visitors" /><category term="collaboration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hardeep Singh’s six-week visit strengthens our collaboration on 2D materials.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog//2025/2025-10-31_hardeep.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog//2025/2025-10-31_hardeep.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New PhD Students Join the Group</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/03/welcome-new-students/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New PhD Students Join the Group" /><published>2025-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/03/welcome-new-students</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/10/03/welcome-new-students/"><![CDATA[<p>This week we were delighted to welcome two new PhD students to the group, Byron Gamble and Sean Egan. To mark the occasion, we had a group lunch at a long-standing and old group favourite, the vegetarian Indian restaurant Chutneys on Drummond St.</p>

<p>It was also a nice opportunity for everyone to spend some time together, including Hardeep, who is visiting from the Indian Institute of Science in Bangalore, Niels, visiting from the University of Iowa, and Georgia, who has been busy lately writing her transfer report.</p>

<p>The two studentships that support Sean and Byron have been made possible by EPSRC/UCL and international collaborations: Sean’s is with the Paul Scherrer Institute (PSI) in Switzerland and Byron’s project is in collaboration with A*STAR in Singapore. The two projects will focus on different aspects of developing the fundamental science needed for atomic-scale control of semiconductors, which underpins potential applications in quantum technology. You can read more about this general research field in the recent <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2399-1984/ada901"><em>Roadmap on atomic-scale semiconductor devices</em></a>, which I coordinated together with five guest editors. The Roadmap brings together contributions from over 50 researchers from around the world, including us at UCL, and reviews 25 years of progress since Kane’s proposal for donor-based qubits in silicon.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-10-04_group_lunch.jpg" alt="Group lunch at Chutneys" />
  <figcaption>Front: Byron and Sean. Middle: Georgia and Niels. Back: Hardeep and Steven.</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="students" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A group lunch to welcome our new students.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-10-04_group_lunch.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-10-04_group_lunch.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our research featured on the cover of Nano Letters</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/24/NanoLetter-Cover/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our research featured on the cover of Nano Letters" /><published>2025-09-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/24/NanoLetter-Cover</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/24/NanoLetter-Cover/"><![CDATA[<p>We are delighted that our work has been featured on the <strong>cover of Nano Letters</strong> (Vol. 25, Issue 38). The cover image (see below) shows an image we took of acceptor wave functions in silicon, showing for the first time how these states can be directly visualized with atomic-resolution scanning tunnelling microscopy. Along with accompanying tunnelling spectroscopy data, and theoretical calculations, our work provides critical insight into the anisotropy of these acceptor states, paving the way for defect-based quantum technologies in silicon.</p>

<p>The experiments were performed at UCL by <strong>Manuel Siegl</strong> and <strong>Holly Hedgeland</strong>, whose STM measurements gave the first direct view of the anisotropic ground-state wave function of an acceptor in silicon. The theoretical work was carried out by <strong>Michael Flatté and his group</strong> at the University of Iowa and the Eindhoven University of Technology, with <strong>Julian Zanon</strong> providing effective-mass calculations and <strong>Joe Sink</strong> contributing tight-binding simulations. This collaboration grew out of Michael’s sabbatical at UCL, illustrating how research visits can spark long-term partnerships and lead to important results.</p>

<p>Through this international collaboration, we have achieved a clear quantitative description of the highly anisotropic acceptor wave function observed at the (100) surface of hydrogen-terminated silicon. The results point towards new strategies for designing quantum technologies in silicon utilising acceptor rather than donor states.</p>

<p><strong>For more, please:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>View the <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/toc/nalefd/25/38">cover and table of contents at Nano Letters</a></li>
  <li>Read the <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c02675">full research article</a></li>
  <li>See coverage at the <a href="https://www.pnas.org/post/journal-club/first-its-kind-image-may-suggest-new-ways-use-silicon-defects-silicon-based-quantum-devices">PNAS Journal Club</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you are interested in <strong>joining our group</strong>, more information is available <a href="/join">here</a>.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-09-24_nanoletters_cover.jpg" alt="Nano Letters cover image" />
  <figcaption>Our research featured on the cover of Nano Letters (Vol. 25, Issue 38) showing acceptor wave functions in silicon</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="publications" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our research featured on the cover of Nano Letters]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-24_nanoletters_cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-24_nanoletters_cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our research highlighted at PNAS Journal Club</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/15/PNAS-coverage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our research highlighted at PNAS Journal Club" /><published>2025-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/15/PNAS-coverage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/15/PNAS-coverage/"><![CDATA[<p>``First-of-its-kind image may suggest new ways to use silicon defects in quantum devices.’’ We are delighted that <strong>PNAS Journal Club</strong> has written about our latest publication, highlighting the significance of our work on imaging acceptor wave functions in silicon.</p>

<p>The article provides a clear and accessible discussion of how our experimental approach reveals new insight into optically active defects.  This feature is an exciting recognition of our group’s efforts to combine atomic-resolution scanning tunnelling microscopy with theoretical modelling. It underscores the potential of engineered defects as building blocks for future quantum technologies.</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can read the PNAS article on the <a href="https://www.pnas.org/post/journal-club/first-its-kind-image-may-suggest-new-ways-use-silicon-defects-silicon-based-quantum-devices">PNAS Journal Club website</a>.</li>
  <li>You can read the full research paper at <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c02675">Nano Letters</a>.</li>
</ul>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-09-15_pnas.jpg" alt="PNAS Journal Club screenshot" />
  <figcaption>PNAS Journal Club article on our work</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="publications" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our research highlighted at PNAS Journal Club]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-15_pnas.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-15_pnas.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New group website launched</title><link href="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/12/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New group website launched" /><published>2025-09-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T20:45:31+00:00</updated><id>https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/12/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schofield-lab.github.io/2025/09/12/first-post/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re pleased to launch our new group website — <a href="https://schofield-lab.github.io">schofield-lab.github.io</a> — and with it, our group blog!</p>

<p>Until now, our pages were hosted within the main UCL website. Ongoing changes to location, styling, and the content management system made it increasingly difficult to keep that site up to date. At the same time, a number of excellent free hosting options for academic websites have become available.</p>

<p>After looking around, we decided that GitHub Pages would be a good fit, and that the <a href="https://github.com/greenelab/lab-website-template">Lab Website Template</a> provided an ideal starting point.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-09-12_1.jpg" alt="The Lab Website template" />
  <figcaption>The Lab Website Template</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The template makes it easy to add our own content without worrying too much about style and layout. Features such as automatic import of citations from the ORCID database are a delight — saving time while increasing the visibility of our research.</p>

<figure class="blog-image">
  <img src="/images/blog/2025/2025-09-12_2.jpg" alt="The new group website" />
  <figcaption>The new group website</figcaption>
</figure>

<hr />

<h3 id="customisations">Customisations</h3>

<p>For anyone interested in setting up a similar page, the <a href="https://greenelab.github.io/lab-website-template/">Lab Website Template</a> comes with detailed instructions. With basic GitHub and Markdown/HTML knowledge, plus Docker if you want to run the site locally, it should be enough to get you started, and the final result is an attractive and easy to maintain and update website.</p>

<p>Having said that, we have made a few modifications to suit our needs:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Search engine optimisation</strong> — added jekyll-seo-tag.</li>
  <li><strong>Cookie management</strong> — included a lightweight JavaScript banner that asks visitors to accept cookies and remembers their choice.</li>
  <li><strong>Mobile styling</strong> — tweaked the CSS so the site looks cleaner on phones and tablets. Images resize automatically, text has more breathing space, and the navigation menu stacks neatly on smaller screens.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="adding-jekyll-seo-tag">Adding jekyll-seo-tag</h3>

<p>Here’s the minimal working recipe to add <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-seo-tag"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll-seo-tag</code></a> in your Docker container:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Add the gem to your Gemfile:</p>

    <div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">gem</span> <span class="s2">"jekyll-seo-tag"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">"~&gt; 2.8"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rebuild the Docker image (no cache):</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>docker build <span class="nt">--no-cache</span> <span class="nt">-f</span> .docker/Dockerfile <span class="nt">-t</span> lab-website-renderer <span class="nb">.</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sanity check (should print a gem path):</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>.docker/run.sh bundle show jekyll-seo-tag
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(Re)launch the site:</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>./.docker/run.sh
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Enable the plugin in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>:</p>

    <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">plugins</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s">jekyll-seo-tag</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Insert the tag in your head include:</p>

    <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">seo</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">%}</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You will also then want to tidy up by removing the hard-coded SEO information in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_includes/meta.html</code>.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h3 id="adding-a-cookie-banner">Adding a Cookie Banner</h3>

<p>To handle cookies, we used the open-source <a href="https://github.com/osano/cookieconsent">CookieConsent</a> library (via CDN) together with a small amount of custom JavaScript. This allows us to run in opt-in mode, defer embedded content such as YouTube or Google Maps until consent is given, and give visitors the option to revoke or reopen settings at any time.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="mobile-styling-tweaks">Mobile Styling Tweaks</h3>

<p>A couple of CSS adjustments helped make the site look better on phones and tablets. Add these rules to your main stylesheet, or create a new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mobile.scss</code> under <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_styles/</code></p>

<div class="language-css highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c">/* Add breathing room for text on small screens */</span>
<span class="nt">body</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nl">padding-left</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0.75rem</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nl">padding-right</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0.75rem</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">@media</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">min-width</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">1025px</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nt">body</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">padding-left</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nl">padding-right</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">@media</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">max-width</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">768px</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nc">.navbar</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nc">.site-nav</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nt">nav</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="nt">role</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s1">"navigation"</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">position</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">static</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nl">top</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">auto</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="nt">header</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nc">.site-header</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nc">.header</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">position</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">relative</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>          <span class="c">/* anchor ::before overlay */</span>
    <span class="nl">overflow</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">hidden</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>            <span class="c">/* clip bg/overlay to header */</span>
    <span class="nl">background-attachment</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">scroll</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* prevent parallax bleed */</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="nt">header</span><span class="nd">::before</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nc">.site-header</span><span class="nd">::before</span><span class="o">,</span>
  <span class="nc">.header</span><span class="nd">::before</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">position</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nb">absolute</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="py">inset</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="cp">!important</span><span class="p">;</span>                    <span class="c">/* top/right/bottom/left: 0 */</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Steven Schofield</name></author><category term="website" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our first post introducing the group blog.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-12_2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://schofield-lab.github.io/images/blog/2025/2025-09-12_2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>